Cameras are used as the primary input device  for a wide range of interaction techniques at
various distances, yet they are constrained by  geometry and require a minimum focal distance.
We present the LensLeech, a deformable silicone  attachment that enables On-Lens Interaction and
can be placed directly on a camera to measure  translation, rotation, and deformation.
This is done by fabricating a clear silicone  body with a lens surface to focus light from the
opposing surface. The resulting image is always in  focus even when the silicone attachment is closer
to the camera than the minimum focal distance  of the lens. On the top surface is a color-coded
marker pattern that allows to uniquely identify  each point even when the material is deformed.
Based on the marker points we can  sense four basic interaction patterns.
The silicone body can be pushed  sideways and used like a joystick.
It can be rotated around the optical axis.
Pressed like a button, and squeezed.
We present application examples using the  LensLeech and various addons for existing devices:
For small, body-worn cameras like action cameras
or lifeloggers with a wide-angle lens  but little physical space for buttons,
the LensLeech can provide the functionality  of a tangible knob to change settings.
With large cameras and interchangeable lenses,  the silicone can be integrated into a lens cap,
making it easy to quickly traverse  large amounts of captured images
on old devices with no touchscreens. However, optical attachments can not only
provide input. When combining the LensLeech with a  set of lenses, a prism, and a beamsplitter, we can
create a hybrid viewfinder. That's a completely  passive smartphone photography add-on that slides
over the display. Visual output is provided  by redirecting a section of the smartphone
screen into an optical viewfinder, providing  a digital overlay over the viewfinder image.
The rear camera remains unobstructed for the  task of taking pictures while the LensLeech
can make use of the front camera to change  settings and act as a shutter release button.
In general, the proposed concept has several  beneficial properties. Silicone attachments are a
simple, inexpensive way of enabling rich, tangible  interaction directly on or above an otherwise
unused camera lens. The silicone is soft and will  not damage glass elements or coatings of lenses.
It requires no hardware modifications  of existing or future devices
and it is unpowered, requiring  only ambient illumination.